<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Get-involveds | James A. Grand</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/get-involved/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Get-involveds</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021-2021 James A. Grand | [License and attributions](/license)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu2193968a47c7885e43f5996d5159098f_13299_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Get-involveds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>MENTORING</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mentoring-statement&#34;&gt;MENTORING STATEMENT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My approach to mentoring students is guided by my belief that the recipe for success&amp;ndash;no matter the context&amp;ndash;is a combination of experience, perseverance, support/encouragement, and luck. As a mentor, I believe my role is to help students find and stick with their passions, recognize and hone their unique strengths, and attempt to model professional and personal behavior that fosters a positive outlook on career success. Given these values, my mentoring philosophy can be summarized as the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I believe my role as a faculty mentor is to&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenge mentees to become independent and critical thinkers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify and connect mentees to beneficial professional opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build the confidence, network, and social capital of mentees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expose mentees to new and alternative perspectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support and facilitate the development of mentees&#39; professional identities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that I am able to pursue these ideals best by fostering mentoring relationships with both undergraduate and graduate students more as a “facilitator” rather than “supervisor.” The opportunity to work with, learn from, and contribute to the development of student collaborators is among the very best parts of my job. This page provides a brief overview of my approach to mentoring both graduate and undergraduate students. If you are interested in working with me, please check out the pages for &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/get-involved/prospective-phd-students&#34;&gt;prospective PhD students&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/get-involved/undergraduate-ra&#34;&gt;undergraduate research assistants&lt;/a&gt; to see if I&amp;rsquo;m currently recruiting and for more information on what it is like to work with me and my lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;graduate-student-mentoring&#34;&gt;GRADUATE STUDENT MENTORING&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe strongly in the importance of graduate students developing a professional identity that is uniquely their own. To this end, I approach graduate education as a true apprenticeship and consider my advisees as essentially junior colleagues for whom it is my job to support and help succeed. This means that I do not just tell my advisees what they should do or how they should do it nor do I simply give them ready-made projects to complete. I prefer to allow graduate students to have their own input and work together with me jointly to develop research. Additionally, I frequently support my advisees’ interests in pursuing topics of study and educational opportunities that may not be directly relevant/applicable to my ongoing work or areas of research. Although this can result in a more diffuse focus in our work and places a heavy onus and sense of personal accountability on my advisees, I believe these experiences are critical to graduate education as they help to simultaneously broaden one&amp;rsquo;s skillsets while establishing a unique specialization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure that my advisees are still making progress towards important milestones, I typically hold weekly one-on-one meetings to discuss both collaborative and independent project work, as well as converse about new ideas, methodologies, and topics of mutual interest. I also conduct a more formalized feedback session with each of my graduate students at least once a year (outside of and in addition to any feedback they receive from standard department-/program-level reviews) in which we discuss accomplishments, reflect on areas/competencies where they feel they are doing well and those where they would like to improve, and talk about career plans and goals for achieving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;undergraduate-student-mentoring&#34;&gt;UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT MENTORING&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of my role as an &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/teaching&#34;&gt;instructor&lt;/a&gt;, I tend to have three primary areas of opportunity for mentoring undergraduate students:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is with undergraduate students who &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/get-involved/undergraduate-ra&#34;&gt;volunteer to work in my lab as research assistants (RAs)&lt;/a&gt;. I strive to maintain an active research lab with approximately 4-6 undergraduate RAs per semester. Although this is a smaller number of students than in many other labs, I find that this allows me to develop more meaningful and developmental relationships and fits my mentoring and working style better. I hold bi-weekly lab meetings for the lab in which we converse about ongoing studies, discuss papers of interest selected and led by undergraduate students, and talk about procedures, advice, and concerns related to graduate school and careers in psychology. We also use time in our lab to work on student-led projects for the department&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate research fair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second is with undergraduate students who volunteer to work as teaching assistants (TAs) for the undergraduate courses I lead. I usually aim to have 1-2 undergraduate TAs in my courses if possible. In semesters where I&amp;rsquo;m fortunate to have student TAs, we meet on a biweekly basis to discuss class operations, basic principles of pedagogy, assessment design, and student engagement. TAs are also given the opportunity to develop and deliver a &amp;ldquo;mini-lecture&amp;rdquo; on a topic of their choosing to the class. In addition to helping come up with and practicing the material, I provide developmental feedback after the mini-lecture to provide students with suggestions and ideas for continuing to improve the communication and teaching skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third is through impromptu meetings with students who contact me and just want to talk. Outside of my normal office hours, I do my best to make myself available to meet with both current and former students to talk about the field of IO psychology, offer advice about internships, graduate school, or careers, and to review application materials for jobs, schools, and fellowships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PROSPECTIVE PHD STUDENTS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/prospective-phd-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/prospective-phd-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Accepting new graduate students --&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;alert alert-success&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class = &#34;row&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class = &#34;col-md-12&#34;&gt;
      I intend to recruit a new PhD student during the current application cycle. Please review the material on this page for more information on my approach to evaluating prospective PhD candidates as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyc.umd.edu/graduate/apply-admission&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;instructions and requirements&lt;/a&gt; for applying to the UMD Psychology Department PhD program.
      &lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;Last updated: 9/14/21&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- Want to but not sure if accepting new graduate students --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;div class = &#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class = &#34;row&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class = &#34;col-md-12&#34;&gt;
        I hope to recruit a new PhD student during the current application cycle. However, I have not received approval to do so at this time. This means there is a possibility that I will NOT be reviewing prospective candidates this year, so please weigh this consideration in your decision to submit an application. I will update the status of my recruitment intentions as soon as I know more, so please check back at a later date.
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;Last updated: 7/8/21&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- Not accepting new graduate students --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;div class = &#34;alert alert-danger&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class = &#34;row&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class = &#34;col-md-12&#34;&gt;
        I will not be recruiting a new PhD student during the current application cycle. However, exceptions may be made for applicants with special funding circumstances (i.e., external funding source, military funding). If this applies to you, please contact me directly to discuss potential opportunities.
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;Last updated: 5/25/21&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This page is intended to provide information, suggestions, and transparency for individuals interested in applying to work with me towards the completion of their PhD. I recognize that the PhD application process is a highly competitve and selective process. However, I also recognize that not every qualified candidate may have had the same access to or the same quality of mentorship, experiences, or opportunities during their undergraduate education or when preparing their application materials. My hope in providing this material is to offer insight into how I review PhD applicants so that prospective candidates can (a) make a more informed decision as to whether they think I would be a good match as an advisor and (b) prepare their application materials in a way that provides me and the review committee the most informative picture of your capabilities, interests, and motivations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the information provided below are my personal views and may not reflect the opinions or advice of any other institution, department, or faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;How do I know if I am a &amp;ldquo;good fit&amp;rdquo; to work with you?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fit&amp;rdquo; has been a &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1744-6570.1996.tb01790.x&#34;&gt;notoriously tricky and suprisingly complex concept to define&lt;/a&gt; and making decisions based too heavily on perceptions of fit has the potential to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shrm.org/hr-today/news/hr-magazine/1118/pages/does-hiring-for-culture-fit-perpetuate-bias.aspx&#34;&gt;perpetuate biases and inequities&lt;/a&gt; if not carefully considered. To this end, I attempt to consider this question from the perspective of a prospective student&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0001879187900431&#34;&gt;supplementary and complementary fit&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supplementary fit&lt;/em&gt; refers to when two parties possess similar capabilities and/or values. Like adding more of your favorite toppings to an ice cream sundae, supplementary fit is improved by the extent to which each party adds to the presence of an already desirable quality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Complementary fit&lt;/em&gt; refers to when the weaknesses/needs of one party are offset by the strengths/resources of the other. Like putting together the pieces of a puzzle, complementary fit is improved by the extent to which each party brings something that the other wants, needs, or benefits from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on these distinctions, I&amp;rsquo;ve listed some aspects of prospective PhD students that are likely to have high complementary and supplementary fit with me, my work, and my approach to training PhD students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supplementary attributes&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inter- and/or trans-disciplinary interests.&lt;/em&gt; As noted in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/research&#34;&gt;research philosophy&lt;/a&gt;, I place high value on integrating ideas across different areas of psychology and other scientific disciplines. If you are primarily only interested in developing knowledge within a single field (i.e., only IO psychology, only social psychology), you are less likely to fit well with my work or approach to PhD training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commitment to research.&lt;/em&gt; I am motivated and do all that I can to support whatever career path my students ultimately find rewarding. However, by signing up for a PhD program in psychology, you are committing to learning how to conduct research and become a social scientist. If you are primarily interested in going directly into a practice/consulting career with little to no interest in engaging in the research process (e.g., designing/conducting studies, writing publications, presenting at conferences), you are less likely to fit well with my work or approach to PhD training.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complementary attributes&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Independence and self-motivation.&lt;/em&gt; As described in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/get-involved/mentoring&#34;&gt;mentoring statement&lt;/a&gt;, I believe that a critical component of graduate training is the development of one&amp;rsquo;s personal and professional identity. I further believe this is difficult to attain if the advisee-advisor relationship is one in which I (as the advisor) simply tell you (as the advisee) exactly what to do or what to work on. Instead, I think this development process is facilitated by approaching the mentoring relationship as one in which I and my advisees are acitve and participative decision-makers in the work we do. This does not mean that I expect my advisees to be wholly &amp;ldquo;on their own&amp;rdquo; from day one or that there will not be times in which I have a specific project in mind for an advisee. However, it does mean that if you are looking for an advisor to hand you ideas, projects, topics, papers, etc. that are ready-to-go and for which your role is mostly to just follow orders to complete the work, you are less likely to fit well with my working and mentoring style.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Research interests/topics.&lt;/em&gt; I am generally less concerned with whether I share the exact same &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; topics of research interest (e.g., team cognition, team processes, training) with my graduate students. Indeed, the opportunity to learn, grow, and be pushed by the unique interests of my students is something I find very rewarding and motivating. However, I have a strong inclination towards approaching research questions/topics from the perspective of complex systems, process mechanisms, and observing behaviors over time. Furthemore, having at least some alignment with my substantive interests can be helpful as there are certainly many topics that I simply won&amp;rsquo;t possess the requisite expertise in to be as effective of a mentor. Nevertheless, so as long as you are open/willing to integrate your ideas and collaborate with me on your specific research interests, you are likely to fit well with my work and approach to PhD training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;What do you think makes a great PhD student?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own strengths and weaknesses that make them unique, and there is certainly no one &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to succeed as a PhD student. In my experience, the best doctoral students I have seen and/or had the opportunity to work with all had some combination of the following capacities. Note this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I think a person must have &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these things to be successful as a PhD candidate; but all successful PhD candidates I&amp;rsquo;ve known had many of these qualities to different degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intellectual curiosity.&lt;/strong&gt; I think a deep passion for learning is a hallmark of great scientists and thinkers. The motivation to always question what we think we know, how or why we think we know things, and to want to pursue new knowledge that helps better understand the world around us is helpful for keeping you going in a PhD program (and beyond).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ways to develop:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read widely (not just within your own area of interests)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen to others talk/present about their work and ask questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seek opportunities to learn from and with people doing things you know little to nothing about
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conscientiousness.&lt;/strong&gt; Being organized, disciplined, and a dependable collaborator and student are helpful for managing the workload and obligations of a PhD program. As a PhD student, you will have a fair bit more independence and choice with respect to when and how you accomplish your work than you did as an undergraduate student. Being able to effectively and efficiently manage your personal and collegial responsibilities is instrumental to meeting important milestones.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ways to develop:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a weekly calendar/scheduler to organize your time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create plans for accomplishing your work with specific tasks, milestones, and deadlines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrive early (rather than on time) for events
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing and communication skills.&lt;/strong&gt; Getting a PhD in the social sciences means you are signing up to become an expert in an area that almost everyone thinks they already know something about. The ability to clearly and concisely convey your knowledge, research, and expertise to your peers, advisors, colleagues, and the public through both written and spoken language is paramount to success both while in and after finishing your PhD program.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ways to develop:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create and use outlines before starting to write or put together a speech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share your writing and practice presentations with others before you submit the final product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seek feedback and help from writing centers and/or peers whose communication skills you admire
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical thinking and argumentation skills.&lt;/strong&gt; All of science involves formulating ideas about how the world works, gathering and interpreting observations, and evaluating evidentiary claims. The capacity to piece together a coherent and sensible argument, defend/support an idea or conclusion, and incorporate new or different knowledge into your worldview are all instrumental to growing as a PhD scientist and practitioner.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ways to develop:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After writing a complete draft of a paper, write a reverse outline where you summarize the points made in each paragraph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice your listening and ask questions &amp;ndash; you&amp;rsquo;d be suprised at how much you can learn about how/why people think about something by simply listening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice your meta-cognitive and self-reflection skills by asking why &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; feel, believe, or react in a particular way
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration skills and prosocial orientation.&lt;/strong&gt; The development and application of scientific knowledge to better understand and improve the world is a &amp;ldquo;team sport.&amp;rdquo; The days of the lone wolf, go-it-your-own scientist are over. Being able to work in and contribute to collaborative efforts through forming supportive and enriching relationships with peers, colleagues, and other stakeholders is a must.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ways to develop:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actively participate in group assignments/projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider what you are giving and receiving in your working relationships and strive to keep them balanced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice giving and receiving construtive feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;How do you evaluate PhD applications?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the term is often over-used and under-defined in higher education admissions, I do my best to adopt a &lt;a href=&#34;https://professionals.collegeboard.org/pdf/understanding-holistic-review-he-admissions.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;holistic review&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of prospective PhD candidates. For my purposes, this means three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no single piece of information (e.g., GPA, standardized test scores, research experience) that I use to determine whether someone is versus is not qualified as an applicant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no specific thresholds of achievement that I rely upon when evaluating applicant qualifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To the extent possible and based on the available information, I do my best to take the context and/or circumstances of an applicants&#39; experiences into account when interpreting their achievements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A low GPA, poor GRE scores, or minimal research experience is thus not guaranteed to tank your application, especially if there were extenuating life circumstances that may have impacted your academic experiences. In such cases however, it is &lt;strong&gt;critical&lt;/strong&gt; to use alternative means to convey your potential for success as a PhD student in your application. For example, you could ask your letter writers to specifically comment on your circumstances and/or provide this information in your personal statement to help me better contextualize your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous section (&amp;ldquo;What do you think makes a great PhD student?&amp;quot;), I listed several competencies that I feel tend to be indicative of success as a PhD student and future scientist-practitioner. When reviewing prospective students, I generally attempt to formulate impressions of each of these facets based on the information provided in your application. There is no single metric that conveys each of these attributes perfectly, but in the interest of transparency, I&amp;rsquo;ve provided examples of some of the indicators I attend to when forming these interpretations below. This list is non-exhaustive and is not intended to reflect my final decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intellectual curiosity&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Potential indicators:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducting independent research (e.g., honor&amp;rsquo;s thesis, first-authored posters, talks, or papers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participating in one or more research labs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attending and/or presenting at conferences or research fairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letters of recommendation
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conscientiousness&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Potential indicators:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience as a research lab manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct experience preparing study materials, collecting data, or conducting analyses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing and/or co-authoring papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Undergraduate GPA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leadership positions in work, school, or community organizations
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing and communication skills&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Potential indicators:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing and/or co-authoring papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducting independent research (e.g., honor&amp;rsquo;s thesis, first-authored posters, talks, or papers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presenting at conferences or research fairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality of writing in the personal statement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality of writing samples
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical thinking and argumentation skills&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Potential indicators:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducting independent research (e.g., honor&amp;rsquo;s thesis, first-authored posters, talks, or papers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing and/or co-authoring papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participating in one or more research labs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality of writing samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letters of recommendation
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration skills and prosocial orientation&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Potential indicators&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leadership positions in work, school, or community organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accomplishments and feedback on group projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participating in one or more research labs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-authoring papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letters of recommendation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-3&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Should I let you know of my interest in working with you? Can I schedule a call with you for more information?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You are welcome to email me to introduce yourself prior to sending your application, but it is not required&amp;ndash;and frankly does not affect your chances of being selected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there is simply not enough time in the day for me to take meetings or phone/video calls with all applicants who wish to chat. I thus have a policy of not scheduling private conversations with any prospecitve student during the application process unless there are particularly unusual circumstances (e.g., military applicants, applicants with atypical funding situations). After I have completed my initial review of all submitted applications, I schedule phone/video calls with a small number of applicants to provide an opportunity for us to further discuss mutual interests and learn more about relevant experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may email me or any of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/people&#34;&gt;current graduate students&lt;/a&gt; if you have specific questions that are not addressed here. However, and prior to doing so, I strongly encourage you to review all the information found on my website as you will likely find answers to many common questions about the work I do and what it would be like to work with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANTS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/undergraduate-ra/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/get-involved/undergraduate-ra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- ACCEPTING RAs --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;div class = &#34;alert alert-success&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class = &#34;row&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class = &#34;col-md-12&#34;&gt;
      I am currently accepting applications for volunteer undergraduate research assistants. Please review the information below on lab expectations and requirements, complete the lab application form, and someone from our lab will follow up to schedule a time to discuss opportunities.
      &lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;Last updated: 9/14/21&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- MAYBE ACCEPTING RAs --&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class = &#34;row&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class = &#34;col-md-12&#34;&gt;
        I don&#39;t currently have openings for additional undergraduate research assistants. However, there is a possibility that additional research projects and/or needs may arise for which we could use assistance. If you&#39;d like to be considered for those opportunities, please review the information below on lab expectations and requirements, complete the lab application form, and someone from our lab will contact you should any opportunities arise.
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;Last updated: 9/14/21&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- NOT ACCEPTING RAs --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;div class = &#34;alert alert-danger&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class = &#34;row&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class = &#34;col-md-12&#34;&gt;
        I don&#39;t currently have openings for additional undergraduate research assistants and do not anticipate further opportunities to participate in the lab. If you are interested in joining the lab at some point in the future, please check back after the current semester has ended and prior to the start of next semester.
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;Last updated: 5/25/21&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting involved in a lab as an undergraduate research assistant (RA) is one of the best ways to learn about how to conduct research, get exposed to new and interesting topics not covered in your coursework, and build your professional network. It&amp;rsquo;s also just a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This page provides information on basic expectations and requirements for participating in the lab as an undergraduate RA as well as answers to some frequently asked questions. If you are considering joining the lab, please review the information below prior to submitting an application. You may also contact me or any of &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/people&#34;&gt;my current graduate students&lt;/a&gt; directly if you have specific questions not addressed here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;What do undergraduate RAs in the lab do?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The undergraduate RAs who collaborate with me and my graduate students participate in many different activities. The specific things you may be asked to help with will vary depending on current projects and needs, but the list below provides examples of some common tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running data collection sessions (i.e., setting up the lab, instructing and assisting participants on study tasks, debriefing participants, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheduling and distributing credits/payments to study participants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with data (i.e., coding, cleaning, analyzing, reviewing/interpreting)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing input/feedback on study ideas and designs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assisting with the development and piloting of lab tasks, measures, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributing to the creation (and, depending on contribution, potentially serving as an author for) posters, presentations and papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading, presenting, and discussing research articles with lab members&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;What can I expect from you and what do you expect of me?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my view, one of the key purposes of participating in a lab is to gain experience, learn new things that may not be part of your coursework, and get to know me, my graduate students, and some of your fellow classmates in a professional non-classroom environment. To that end, here are my commitments to those collaborating with me in the lab and the commitments I expect in return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-you-can-expect-of-me&#34;&gt;What you can expect of me:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will be available to provide advice, suggestions, and guidance to you on topics related to your coursework, graduate school, and career options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will do my best to provide you with opportunities and experiences that are important, relevant, and useful to your goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will always treat you and all members of the lab with respect and courtesy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will ask for and take your input into consideration on questions and decisions relevant to the lab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wlil do my best to support and accommodate any unique life or school circumstances that may affect your participation in the lab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-i-expect-of-you&#34;&gt;What I expect of you:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect you to be an active participant in and willing volunteer for lab-relevant tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect you to fulfill any and all formal obligations as part of your membership in the lab (i.e., attending meetings, fulfilling time commitments and course credit requirements, completing any required trainings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect you to communicate with me and my graduate students regularly (especially when asked for your input/assistance on lab-relevant tasks or when unusual circumstances arise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect you to treat me and all members of the lab with respect and courtesy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect you to interact with all research participants in our lab in a professional and respectful manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A failure to meet any of these expectations in a reasonable manner may result in dismissal from the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Can I participate in the lab for course credit?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The University of Maryland psychology department offers the &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyc.umd.edu/undergraduate/psyc-forms&#34;&gt;option for undergraduate RAs to earn course credit by enrolling in PSYC479&lt;/a&gt;. However, to participate in my lab for credit, you must meet the following eligibility requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;at-least-one-of-the-following-must-be-true&#34;&gt;At least one of the following must be true&amp;hellip;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;myRA&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;myRA&#34;&gt;
  Have participated as an undergraduate RA in my lab for at least one semester
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;otherRA&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;otherRA&#34;&gt;
  Have participated as an undergraduate RA in another faculty member&#39;s lab for at least one semester (requires informal recommendation from the faculty member)
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;myTA&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;myTA&#34;&gt;
  Have participated as an undergraduate TA for one of my classes for at least one semester
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;-and-all-of-the-following-must-be-true&#34;&gt;&amp;hellip; and all of the following must be true:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;raRequirements&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;raRequirements&#34;&gt;
  Are a junior or senior with at least a 3.0 GPA and at least 9 credits in PSYC (these are deparment requirements)
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;raHours&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;raHours&#34;&gt;
  Can commit a minimum of 3 hours per week (i.e., 45 hours total per semester) to the lab
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;raMtg&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;raMtg&#34;&gt;
  Can attend all lab meetings (i.e., no regularly scheduled conflicts with lab meeting time)
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;form-check&#34;&gt;
  &lt;input id = &#34;raAssignment&#34; class = &#34;form-check-input&#34; type = &#34;checkbox&#34; value = &#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;label class = &#34;form-check-label&#34; for = &#34;raAssignment&#34;&gt;
  Will complete either a short paper or presentation by the end of the semester on a topic agreed upon with Prof. Grand
  &lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Please note that if you do not meet the above criteria, you are still eligible to apply for the lab as a volunteer undergraduate RA for no course credit. 
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-3&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;How much time am I expected to commit to the lab?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The minimum time commitment I ask of all undergraduate RAs is &lt;strong&gt;3 hours per week&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e., 45 hours total per semester). Note that your time commitment will be greater if you are enrolled in &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyc.umd.edu/undergraduate/psyc-forms&#34;&gt;PSYC479&lt;/a&gt; for more than 1 course credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note that I expect all RAs to attend our regularly scheduled lab meetings.&lt;/strong&gt; Only under very special circumstances will I allow an undergraduate RA to be part of the lab but not attend lab meetings. Attending and participating in these meetings is a critical part of the lab experience. It is one of the best ways for you to stay involved and get to know me and the other members of the lab&amp;ndash;plus it&amp;rsquo;s more fun when everyone is present! Lab meetings are typically held bi-weekly, run for one hour, and count towards your expected time commitment. The specific dates and times for lab meetings will be set prior to the beginning of each semester; I will do my best to accomodate people&amp;rsquo;s course schedules, but it is not always possible for me to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-4&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;What projects will I work on?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The specific projects that we do in the lab and to which you might contribute varies from semester to semester. It is especially common for undergraduate RAs to work closely with my current graduate students on their thesis and dissertation research. To get a sense for some of the types of projects I do though, please check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/projects-home&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-5&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Can I do an independent research project or honor&amp;rsquo;s thesis with you?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes! Please contact me directly to discuss availability and options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I strongly encourage and assist all RAs working in the lab with preparing a poster submission for our department&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyc.umd.edu/undergraduate/undergraduate-research-day&#34;&gt;annual research fair&lt;/a&gt;. This may involve presenting data we&amp;rsquo;re currently collecting in the lab, data that has been previously collected by me or others in the lab, or new data that any RAs are interested in collecting for their research idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
