<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teams | James A. Grand</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/teams/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/teams/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Teams</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021-2021 James A. Grand | [License and attributions](/license)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu2193968a47c7885e43f5996d5159098f_13299_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Teams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/teams/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational architecture for studying team-based systems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/team-system-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/team-system-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;funding-sources&#34;&gt;Funding Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ari.altess.army.mil/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Army Research Institute for the Behavioral and Social Sciences&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: W911NF-14-1-0026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-collaborators&#34;&gt;Key Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/michaelbraun/&#34;&gt;Mike Braun&lt;/a&gt; (DePaul University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/gorankuljanin/&#34;&gt;Goran Kuljanin&lt;/a&gt; (DePaul University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/stevekozlowski/&#34;&gt;Steve Kozlowski&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of South Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/georgiachao/&#34;&gt;Georgia Chao&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of South Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern work environment in which organizations operate has continued its trajectory towards increasingly more complex and interdependent task demands that require rapid, flexible, and adaptive responses to the unexpected. In response, a world-wide restructuring of work around teams has occurred. As teams have become the dominant unit of work, team-based systems composed of teams of teams have also begun to emerge as a new organizational form (e.g., multiteam systems, MTSs). Managing and enhancing those facets that contribute to the effectiveness of teams and team-based systems depends on understanding the dynamic forces which influence how individuals within and between teams combine their efforts to successfully fulfill task demands in uncertain environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this stream of research, my colleageus and I have sought to develop a highly flexible and generalizable architecture for building, integrating, and testing theory related to team and team-based system effectiveness. Our work is deeply rooted in the principles of complex adaptive systems and adopts the perspective that collective functioning is an emergent property of the behaviors, choices, and perceptions of individual members of the collective; their relational interactions and influences; and the social and task environments in which those individuals operate. To this end, our research group has advanced a scalable and integrative agent-based model that allows us to represent various attributes and decision processes of individual team members, task demands, and the formation of interpersonal perceptions and influence that can affect interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have conducted numerous simulation studies with the model to evaluate its correspondence with existing research/theory as well as probe and reveal insights into several compelling questions. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does the composition of a team (i.e., the constellation of skills, demographics, dispostional attributes, etc.) affect the emergence of cohesion, influence, and performance under different task environments?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can a team be more (or less) than the sum of its parts?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and in what ways can a single individual influence an entire collective?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When can maximizing the performance of a single team come at the expense of overall system performance in a MTS?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our ongoing research, we aim to extend the architecture to permit more fluid team-based systems (e.g., changing team memberships), more variable task environments (e.g., unexpected changes), and more robust mechanisms for representing individual/system adaptation (e.g., goal systems).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of collective and distributed knowledge in teams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/team-knowledge-emergence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/team-knowledge-emergence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;funding-sources&#34;&gt;Funding Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.onr.navy.mil/en/Science-Technology/Departments/Code-34/All-Programs/human-bioengineered-systems-341/command-decision-making&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Office of Naval Research, Command Decision Making Program&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: N00014-09-1-0519&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ari.altess.army.mil/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Army Research Institute for the Behavioral and Social Sciences&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: W911NF-14-1-0026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-collaborators&#34;&gt;Key Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/michaelbraun/&#34;&gt;Mike Braun&lt;/a&gt; (DePaul University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/gorankuljanin/&#34;&gt;Goran Kuljanin&lt;/a&gt; (DePaul University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/stevekozlowski/&#34;&gt;Steve Kozlowski&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of South Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/georgiachao/&#34;&gt;Georgia Chao&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of South Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the concept of team cognition was first proposed and popularized in the organizational sciences, a great deal of theory and empirical research has accumulated examining its impact on team functioning and effectiveness. Although there are now numerous different conceptulations of team cognitio, the concept has most commonly been examined from the perspective of shared &lt;em&gt;mental models&lt;/em&gt; (extent to which individual members of a team hold similar cogntiive representations of the team and its task) and &lt;em&gt;transactive memory systems&lt;/em&gt; (extent to which collectively relevant knowledge about the team and its task is distributed across yet accessible to individual members). There is sufficient meta-analytic evidence to suggest that both conceptualizations of team cognition are important to the performance and decision quality of teams. However, a coherent understanding of &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; groups develop, integrate, and adapt these forms of shared cognition remains incomplete. That is, little attention has been directed towards the dynamic processes through which knowledge is acquired, compiles, and manifests within teams. The manner by which team knowledge is created and sustained remains a “black box.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lack of theoretical and empirical attention towards unpacking this black box and revealing the processes responsible for team knowledge emergence is problematic for at least two reasons. First, the development and maintenance of knowledge at the team level inherently involves intra- and inter-member processes unfolding over time. However, what these processes are and how they interact to facilitate team cognition are not well explicated. Second, ignoring the process of team knowledge emergence limits inferences about why teams may be more or less successful at achieving desired levels of team cognition. Focusing on static, variable-to-variables relationships between predictors and team knowledge outcomes (i.e., higher team ability -&amp;gt; better team cognition) can suggest conditions that correlate with the development of collective knowledge. However, such research does not provide insight into &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; these conditions lead to improved knowledge outcomes. Systematically exploring these questions requires concerted efforts to develop more precise theory and conduct more focused empirical research that capture the events, actions, and cognitive processes that contribute to the development of both individually held and collectively shared knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary focus of research in the domain of team cognition is thus directly oriented towards specifying and studying the dynamic processes involved in developing team cognition. In some of my initial work in this domain, my colleagues and I advanced a formal theory and computational model that elaborated several core concepts and mechanisms of knowledge emergence in teams. Our simulations with the model revealed several leverage points for facilitating convergent team cognition, such as improving the rates at which individual members learn information and regulating the rates at which information is shared/exchanged by individuals. We then constructed a novel team knowledge-building task and conducted an empirical study which lent support to these model predictions and therefore the core model mechanisms. In future research in this domain, I am interested in further examining the effects of individual vs. joint attention, the role of path dependence in team knowledge and decision-making (i.e., extent to which previously known/shared information and decisions shapes subsequent attention to information and choices by teams), and incorporating the effects of goals and differences in individuals&#39; understanding of &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rdquo; interpretations impact the emergence of collective knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facilitating the transfer and impact of team and leadership training on patient outcomes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/translational-sim-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/translational-sim-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;funding-sources&#34;&gt;Funding Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ahrq.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: 1R18HS020295-01&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: 1R18HS022458-01A1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cdmrp.army.mil/dmrdp/default&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Defense Medical Research and Development Program, JPC-1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: W81XWH-15-1-0403&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cdmrp.army.mil/dmrdp/default&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Defense Medical Research and Development Program, JPC-1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Award #: W81XWH-18-1-0089&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-collaborators&#34;&gt;Key Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/rosefernandez/&#34;&gt;Rose Fernandez&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/lizarosenman/&#34;&gt;Liza Rosenman&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of Washington)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/stevekozlowski/&#34;&gt;Steve Kozlowski&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of South Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/authors/georgiachao/&#34;&gt;Georgia Chao&lt;/a&gt; (Univ of South Florida)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contemporary healthcare system is often described as a “team sport” that relies heavily on coordination within and between teams of medical professionals to deliver patient care and manage increasingly complex processes. To this end, communication, teamwork skills, and effective team leadership have emerged as crucial elements to the provision of high quality healthcare and patient safety than ever before. Indeed, failures in these crucial aspects of team functioning have been directly linked with both increased medical errors and adverse patient events. Unfortunately, training and well-validated instructional guidance for developing effective team and leadership skills is a comparatively small component of most medical and continuing education programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working closely with collaborators across a variety of healthcare disciplines, I design and conduct validation studies that target the development of generalizable training, assessment, and feedback methods aimed at improving the teamwork and leadership skills of healthcare professionals. The majority of work I conduct in this area is in emergency medicine contexts, in which individuals are tasked with working as part of ad hoc, multidisciplinary teams to perform complex patient care and medical decision-making under dynamic and time pressured conditions. These factors present considerable challenges for both team communication and coordination, and thus pose significant threats to patient safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within this line of research, my colleagues and I focus heavily on improving the quality and effectiveness of &lt;em&gt;simulation-based training techniques&lt;/em&gt; (i.e., using artificial patients/scenarios as a stimulus for trainees to learn and practice skills) for improving the team and leadership capabilities of medical students/residents. Through this research stream, we focus on developing accessible and generalizable recommendations/guidance on how to structure training opportunities, assessment and evaluative methodologies, and deliver feedback to learners that can be implemented by both medical researchers and educators. Additionally, we have developed multiple team skills and leadership training programs, and have demonstrated that the behaviors/skills taught in our simulation-based trainings transfer to actual care settings with real patients and exhibit a measureable impact on the quality of medical care provided.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
